Finding Aid for Wesley H. Maurer Papers, 1924-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Wesley H. Maurer Papers 1924-1995, 1930-1970
Maurer, Wesley Henry, 1897-
4.75 linear feet
88544 Aa 2
Wesley H. Maurer, Sr., was a professor of journalism at the University of Michigan, and served as chair of the department from 1949 to 1966. He actively critiqued the journalism field, and was very involved in improving journalism education. Maurer was instrumental in establishing the internship program at the University of Michigan, and bought newspapers to provide students with work-experience, two of which he continued to operate until his death. Maurer was also involved in promoting democracy and free speech in the community.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Wesley Maurer, Sr. (donor no. 7107 ) and came to the library in 2000.
The collection is open to research.
Wesley Henry Maurer, Sr. was born on January 19, 1897 in Bunker Hill, Illinois. He married Margaret E. Weber in 1944. They had three children: Margaret, Wesley H. Jr., and Marilyn.
Maurer was educated at the University of Missouri, earning his A.B. degree in economics in 1921, his B.S. degree in Public and Business Administration in 1922, and his B.J. degree in journalism in 1923. He served as an editor on various papers before becoming an instructor at the University of Michigan from 1924 to 1925. He was an assistant professor of journalism at Ohio University from 1925 to 1928.
Maurer re-joined the University of Michigan faculty in 1928, as an instructor. He became an associate professor in 1932, and a professor in 1948. Maurer became chair of the journalism department in 1949 and served in that capacity until 1966, when he retired.
As a professor, Maurer emphasized the importance of practical experience. He was instrumental in improving the fellowship and internship programs of the Department of Journalism. He also established the Michigan Journalist, an experimental newspaper written by students that was circulated to publishers, editors, and teachers of journalism. Maurer bought several newspapers, including the Harbor Light, and the Mackinac Island Town Crier, which employed mostly students. Maurer also owned and operated the St. Ignace News and the Cedarville Weekly Wave (which later folded into the St. Ignace News).
While he was teaching at the University of Michigan, Maurer lead an adult education discussion group called "American Affairs and World Events." It met once a week in Detroit. During each session, the group discussed a controversial topic, based on the abstract of a book prepared by one of the members. Maurer began the class in 1929 and continued until 1967. At the time, it was the oldest discussion group of its kind in the country.
After his retirement, Maurer continued operating the St. Ignace weekly paper and the summer weekly paper the Town Crier on Mackinac Island, functioning as editor and publisher, until his death in 1995 at the age of 98.
The Maurer collection documents Wesley H. Maurer's career as a journalist and as a teacher of journalism. The collection has been arranged into the following series: Personal; Department of Journalism Administration; Michigan Federation of Teachers; Papers and Speeches; and Teaching.
Subjects:
Journalists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Medicine--Michigan.; American newspapers.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Journalism.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Davis, Chandler.; Journalism--Study and teaching--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Michigan Federation of Teachers.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Maurer, Wesley Henry, 1897-; Newspaper industry--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Journalism.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Journalism--Students.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal
  Personal (0.5 linear feet) includes biographical information, awards, correspondence, and a few poems that Maurer wrote about journalism. The correspondence (1933-1992) often concerns issues in journalism.
  - Award of Degrees, Excellence in Journalism, and Community Service 1921-1994 (Box 1)
  - Award of "Teacher of the Year" by the Adult Education Association of Michigan 1965 (Box 1)
  - Biographical
    - Articles 1966-1993 (Box 1)
    - Biographical Sketches (Box 1)
    - Entry in Who's Who in American Journalism, 22nd ed. (Box 1)
    - Eulogy 1995 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1933-1992, undated, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Governor Blanchard 1983-1985 (Box 1)
  - Poems (Box 1)
  - Resumes (Box 1)
- Department of Journalism Administration
  Department of Journalism Administration (1 linear foot) covers materials pertaining to the functioning of the department. It includes department missions and goals, which are also emphasized in the department reviews of 1959 and 1963. There are also materials on the fellowship and internship programs that Maurer helped establish, and the newspapers which he ran and used to provide experience for students. Also included are materials on the seventy-fifth anniversary of the department, in 1966. The planning for the event, the speeches and discussions during the event, and Maurer's retirement celebration are documented. Also of note are materials pertaining to Maurer's defense of free speech during the 1940's and 1950's against concerns of Communism, including the controversy surrounding the dismissal of Professor H. Chandler Davis of the University of Michigan.
  - Chairman of the Department duties (Box 1)
  - Communism and Free Speech
    - Articles 1949-1954, undated (Box 1)
    - H. Chandler Davis Dismissal 1954-1956 (Box 1)
    - Student Dismissals 1940 (Box 1)
  - Course Syllabi 1953 (Box 1)
  - Department History (Box 1)
  - Department Mission (Box 1)
  - Department Reviews
    - 1959 1963, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Developing Department Plans 1948-1966, undated (Box 1)
  - Department Seventy-Fifth Anniversary
    - Articles and Press Releases 1966 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - With Panelists, before event 1966 (Box 1)
      - With Panelists, after event 1966 (Box 1)
      - After the Anniversary 1966 (Box 1)
      - With people who attended 1966 (Box 1)
      - With people who did not attend 1966 (Box 1)
    - Maurer's Retirement Celebration 1966 (Box 1)
    - Maurer's Speech, "Theme of the Dialogue" (draft) 1966 (Box 1)
    - Program and "Epigrammatic Triads," 1966 (Box 1)
    - Sesquicentennial Press Kit 1966 (Box 2)
    - Transcription of Speeches and Discussions 1966 (Box 2)
  - Enrollment and Graduation Statistics 1946-1958 (Box 2)
  - Fellowship Program 1948-1960 (Box 2)
  - Film Strip, "Principles of Make-Up: critiquing newspaper page layouts," 1941, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Film Strip Series Proposal, current events for secondary students (Box 2)
  - Graduate Program Mission and Policies 1936-1960 (Box 2)
  - Guest Lecturers 1947-1963 (Box 2)
  - Internship Program
    - Employer Reports 1955-1965 (Box 2)
    - Establishing the Internship Program 1957 (Box 2)
    - International News Project 1954 (Box 2)
    - Papers on the Program 1957-1966 (Box 2)
    - Student Reports
      - The Harbor Light 1969-1970 (Box 2)
      - The Toledo Blade 1964 (Box 2)
      - WFDF Radio 1965 (Box 2)
  - Newspapers
    - Harbor Light
      - Intern Project Proposal (Box 2)
      - New Feature: News you might have missed 1971 (Box 2)
      - Selling the Paper 1969-1971, undated (Box 2)
      - Special Report on the Harbor Light and the Town Crier September 30, 1970 (Box 2)
    - "The Michigan Journalist: Experimental Newspaper for the Practice of Professional Journalism" (Box 2)
    - The St. Ignace News 1969-1993 (Box 2)
    - The Town Crier, Mackinac Island (Box 2)
  - Photographs of department events and students working (Box 2)
  - Professor Class Loads 1959 (Box 2)
  - Professor Kenneth Stewart Appointments 1948-1965, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Requesting the Department become part of LS&A 1927 (Box 2)
  - Researching changing the name from "Department" to "School," 1952 (Box 2)
  - Scholarships in Journalism 1955-1959 (Box 2)
  - Undergraduate Program Mission and Policies (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan News Service Press Releases 1954-1966 (Box 2)
  - The University of Michigan Press 1952 (Box 2)
- Michigan Federation of Teachers
  Michigan Federation of Teachers (0.25 linear feet) consists of papers pertaining to the University of Michigan and Ann Arbor chapter of the American Federation of Teachers, the teacher's union. Maurer was a charter member. The union was involved primarily with defending teachers from unlawful firing and support of the tenure act. Maurer was also involved in creating a film strip on the need for financial aid for higher education in 1940 that was widely circulated.
  - University of Michigan and Ann Arbor Chapter No. 284 Charter from the American Federation of Teachers 1934 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1933-1956, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Financial Aid Filmstrip, Script and Images 1940, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Papers and Resolutions, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Papers and Speeches
  Papers and Speeches (1.5 linear feet) include articles Maurer wrote and notes for speeches he gave on a variety of topics. Articles often have edited drafts and correspondence reacting to them. Topics include Maurer's critique of the journalism profession, community activism and democracy, the state of the education system, community health issues, and the Church. The articles entitled "Maurer Philosophy" provide a synthesis of his beliefs about news and journalism, developed over the course of his career. The folders "Lectures #1-8" are Maurer's designation, and have an accompanying index of the papers in each folder. These papers cover many topics, with a focus on democracy and journalism education.
  - Correspondence 1950-1987, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Biography of Marlen Pew (correspondence) (Box 2)
  - "The Church and Economic Life," 1946-1947, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - The Church: Trends in Religion (Box 2)
  - The Church: "What Beatitude Means to Me" (Box 2)
  - "The Church and Youth" (Box 2)
  - Citizenship and Civil Liberties 1977, undated (Box 2)
  - "Citizen's Council of Ann Arbor: A Tool for Democracy" (Box 2)
  - "The College of Literature, Science and the Arts Celebrates its One Hundredth Birthday" (Box 2)
  - Community Membership Relations Representatives (CMRR) Public Relations Seminar, Improving Union Publications 1967-1969 (Box 3)
  - Community Newspapers 1989, undated (Box 3)
  - Crime News Reporting 1951, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - "The Democracy of Learning", 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Education 1929, undated (Box 3)
  - Education in the Field of Journalism, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Education in Health (Box 3)
  - "Establishment of Community Forces for Health Education" (Box 3)
  - Film Strip Script on Benedict Arnold (Box 3)
  - Film Strip Script on Community (Box 3)
  - Incomplete Papers (Box 3)
  - "Keeping Alive a Sense of Human Worth," radio address prepared as publicity chairman of Washtenaw County 1941 (Box 3)
  - Index to Lectures 1-8 (Box 3)
  - Lectures #1-8 1932-1962 (Maurer's numbering scheme), 8 folders (Box 3)
  - Maurer Philosophy of Education and Citizenship, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Maurer Philosophy of Events, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Maurer Philosophy of News 1967 (Box 3)
  - Medical Care in Essex, Ontario, series of 3 articles, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Medical Care in Michigan, series of 10 articles 1933, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - News copy and editorial contests 1918-1919, 1950, undated (Box 4)
  - Part 2, "The Climate of Peace" (Box 4)
  - Part 3, "The High Cost of Failure" (Box 4)
  - Part 5, "The Budget of Abundance" (Box 4)
  - The Press, history and issues 1987, undated (Box 4)
  - "The Press in Labor Controversies," 1928-1931, undated (Box 4)
  - "Propaganda," 1939 (Box 4)
  - "Propaganda Today" (Box 4)
  - Reporting on Crime and the Justice System 1952, undated (Box 4)
  - Review of the accuracy of the Detroit Free Press accounts on Judge George Crockett Jr. 1969 (Box 4)
  - Review of "A Semantic Interpretation of Relativity" (Box 4)
  - "The Spectrum of Thought or The Conflict of Contemporary Ideas" (Box 4)
  - "What is Freedom of the Press?" debate with Detroit Free Press editor Malcolm Bingay 1935 (Box 4)
- Teaching
  Teaching (1.5 linear feet) covers all of Maurer's teaching activities. The papers from the Department of Journalism classes include syllabi, and notes for lectures and class activities. There are also papers from his guest lectures series in Quito, Ecuador, in September 1964, at the Center for Advanced Study of Journalism for Latin American (CIESPAL). Of special significance are the papers regarding the American Affairs and World Events adult-education discussion group. Maurer created the group in 1929 and continued to lead it until 1967. Members of the class discussed current, controversial issues. The papers include lists of the books and topics discussed each year, as well as the group's newsletter and advertising for the class. Also of note is correspondence with former students, reflecting on their valuable experiences with him as a professor.
  - Correspondence with former students 1950-1993, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - American Affairs and World Events
    - Administrative Correspondence 1944-1966, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Course Description 1955-1970 (Box 4)
    - Course Materials 1949-1970, undated, 11 folders (Box 4)
    - "The Spotlight," (newsletter sent to group members) 1965-1971 (Box 4)
  - Center for Advanced Study of Journalism for Latin American (CIESPAL)
    - Arranging the Lectures 1964 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence (Maurer's reactions to the seminar) 1964-1967 (Box 4)
    - Department of State Debriefing 1964-1965 (Box 4)
    - Publications and Bulletins by CIESPAL 1964-1965 (Box 4)
    - Synopsis of the 20 Lectures by Maurer, "Freedom of the Press and A Philosophy of News," 1964 (Box 4)
  - Journalism 91
    - Class Exercises
      - Reporting on Events, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Reporting on Ideas (Box 4)
    - Class Notes
      - Reporting on Ideas (Box 4)
      - Reporting on Interviews and Reporting on Journalism (Box 4)
  - Journalism 130-131, Communication Agencies and Public Opinion, Class Notes (Box 5)
  - Journalism 407 (141)
    - Class Notes
      - #1-4 (Maurer's numbering scheme), 4 folders (Box 5)
      - Freedom of the Press (Box 5)
      - Freedom to Publish (Box 5)
      - Law of the Press Notes and Outlines 1963 (Box 5)
    - Syllabus 1961-1965, undated, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Journalism 801, Discussion Schedule 1966 (Box 5)
  - Journalism 808, Community Newspaper, Syllabus (Box 5)
  - Residential College Freshman Seminar
    - Student Reports on the First Class 1967 (Box 5)
    - Syllabus (Box 5)
    - Revised Syllabus (Box 5)
  - Teaching Appointments
    - Job Search 1924-1930, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Ohio University 1925-1928, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - University of Michigan 1924-1969, 2 folders (Box 5)